<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Information on Crushing C.O.D.E</title>
    <link>https://crushingcode.github.io/tags/information/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Information on Crushing C.O.D.E</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - Nishant Srivastava</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2016 10:54:24 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://crushingcode.github.io/tags/information/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rewriting The History</title>
      <link>https://crushingcode.github.io/rewriting-the-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2016 10:54:24 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://crushingcode.github.io/rewriting-the-history/</guid>
      <description>Most of us are engineers and at the end of the day humans. So basically we all are bound to make mistakes. As an Engineer we make such mistakes in code quite often and even if we do not admit it , they do exist. How many times have you published your code to a public VCS such as Github/Bitbucket with the credentials and then pulled down the repository only to reset the whole history and re-publish the new repository with the credentials cleaned out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do you like to ADB?</title>
      <link>https://crushingcode.github.io/do-you-like-to-adb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 10:54:24 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://crushingcode.github.io/do-you-like-to-adb/</guid>
      <description>Lets face it we all have been there , trying to fiddle with managing our emulators and dev devices. And at max we would do is try to manually manage it. Let me make this clear I am not talking about tests here as that&amp;rsquo;s all related to the code. My focus here is on managing the device/emulator that&amp;rsquo;s paired with your dev environment/system (..and to your IDE - Android Studio , if you still use Eclipse you are simply oblivious to the joys of coding in Android [here is a long blank stare from me to you] ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Whats in the APK?</title>
      <link>https://crushingcode.github.io/whats-in-the-apk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 10:54:24 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://crushingcode.github.io/whats-in-the-apk/</guid>
      <description>If I give you the code of an android app and ask you to provide me information regarding the android app like minSdkVersion, targetSdkVersion, permissions, configurations, almost anyone who knows how to code an android app would provide it to me in a few minutes. But what if I gave you an android apk file and then ask you to answer for the same 🤔 Its tricky if you try to think at the very first instance.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>